Louis J. Budd Papers and compilation of Mark Twain Resources, 1980-2008, undated
Elmira College
- SERIES 2: CARICATURES, 1980 - 2008; The series primarily consists of reproductions, negatives and prints of Mark Twain caricatures. Louis Budd states in a letter to the National Portrait Gallery in 1989, “For some years I have been gathering caricatures of Mark Twain, especially those done during 
  - Pilgrims Luncheon/Bystander, 10 July 1907 -- "Mark Twain's Visit: The veteran humorist amuses the pilgrims' club with some new jokes at the savoy luncheon held in his honour", undated
  - "London Tribune," 10 July 1907, undated
  - "Liverpool Daily Post and Mercury," 11 July 1907 -- "John Bull and the vanishing cups", undated
  - "Chicago Inter-Ocean," 13 July 1907, p. 1 -- "Mark Twain Leaves England--and the Ascot cup is still missing", undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 20 July 1907: Mark Twain, Mrs. Eddy, King Leopold, undated
  - "Judge," 27 July 1907, undated
  - "Christian Advocate," 1 August 1907 -- "Doctor's all or more innocents abroad", undated
  - "Life," 1 August 1907 --"England Likes Mark Twain", undated
  - "Life," 29 August 1907 -- T. S. Tousey caricature, undated
  - "Success Magazine," September 1907: Yankee in King Edwards Court -- "Impressions by 'Dwig'", undated
  - "New York Evening Journal," 20 September 1907: Mark Twain and H. H. Rogers by T. E. Powers, "Two Eminent Humorists", undated
  - "Harper's Weekly," 12 October 1907: Mark Rockefeller -- "From the Nature-Fakers' Gallery", undated
  - "Literary Digest," 19 October 1907: Oxford procession, undated
  - "New York World," 24 November 1907, undated
  - "Life," 28 November 1907 --Transparency, undated
  - "New York American," 1 December 1907, undated
  - "New York World," 10 December 1907; Also 24 April 1910 -- "Mark Twain in After Dinner Speech at His Best, as Cesare Saw Him", undated
  - "New York World," 15 December 1907 -- "The most remarkable seen in New York this season", undated
  - "Pleiades Club," 22 December 1907 by Anderson, undated
  - James A. Shepperd, 1907 -- Correspondence seeking caricature from the National Portrait Gallery, 1989
  - "New York Times," 19 January 1908 -- "Mark and Mary a Novel Gyroscopic Toy--Combines Science and Laughter, undated
  - "Saturday Evening Post," 15 February 1908: Re: Stewart -- "I am Just Back from the Holy Land", undated
  - "New York World," 20 February 1908 -- "Some Distinguished New Yorkers Who Attended the Pilgrims Dinner", undated
  - "New York Times," 1 March 1908 -- "Mark Twain prefers to be put at the end of the programme", undated
  - "Collier's," 10 April 1909 -- "Indoor America", undated
  - "New York American," 19 April 1908, undated
  - "Vanity Fair," 13 May 1908: Spy caricature, undated
  - "New York World," 19 September 1908 -- "Mark Twain's home, the two burglars, their captor and the Twain kittens", undated
  - "New York World," 26 December 1908 -- "Malefactors of Great Wealth Club", undated
  - "New York Herald," 29 December 1908: "Mark Twain has 'Elephant' on his Hands", undated
  - Max Beerbohm, c. 1908, undated
  - "The New Planet/Harper's Weekly," 30 January 1909, p. 13, undated
  - Scrapbook, January 1909 by Mark Fenderson -- "good natured portraits", undated
  - "New York World," 28 February 1909 -- "The World's Championship Belt", undated
  - "Norfolk (Va.) Ledger Dispatch," 5 April 1909 -- Text of article, no image, 1999
  - "Current Literature," June 1909 -- "Cloud effects", undated
  - "Coburn Negatives, late 1908-1909 -- Two twain portrait color negatives, 1980
  - Art young: Mark Twain walking on Fifth Avenue, undated
  - "New York Times," 6 February 1910 -- Mark Twain chased by Denmark, undated
  - Red Lewis: Mark Twain as Huck Finn, undated
  - "New York World,": Mark Twain and Dickens by Anderson, undated
  - Mark Twain as a Notorious Smoker -- photograph, undated
  - Fudge caricature, undated
  - Carlo de Fornaro? -- Notecards and article, no image, undated
  - "Chicago Daily News," 22 April 1910 -- "The Magic River", undated
  - "Chicago Record-Herald," 22 April 1910 -- "The Babies; They Comfort Us in Our Sorrows, Let us not Forget Them in Our Festivities", undated
  - "Chicago Tribune," 22 April 1910 -- Caricature by Briggs, undated
  - "New York American," 22 April 1910: R. Carter/also 2d item, undated
  - "Lewiston Evening Journal," 22 April 1910 -- "Hall of Fame", undated
  - "St. Louis Post-Dispatch," 22 April 1910 -- "Pilot", undated
  - "St. Louis Republic," 22 April 1910 -- "Humorist whose eventful career has been closed by death", undated
  - "Springfield Illinois State Journal," 22 April 1910 -- "Stayed is the Hand that made world laugh and weep" by Grue, undated
  - "Wheeling (W. Va) Register," 22 April 1910 -- "Mark Twain, Most Picturesque Figure in Literature, is Dead", undated
  - "Atlanta Journal," 23 April 1910 -- "Uncle Sam Mourns", undated
  - "Baltimore American," 23 April 1910: Thorndike -- "There is a Time to Laugh and There is a Time to Weep", undated
  - "Cleveland Plain Dealer," 23 April 1910 -- "Down the River", undated
  - "Denver (Rocky Mountains) News," 23 April 1910 -- "The Old Pilot's Last Voyage" by Gilbert, undated
  - "Knoxville Journal and Tribune," 23 April 1910 --"The Vacant Chair", undated
  - "Los Angeles Times," 23 April 1910 -- "Among the Immortals", undated
  - "Nashville American," 23 April 1910 -- Wetterau, undated
  - "New York World," 23 April 1910: Obituary Cartoon -- "The Last Voyage", undated
  - "St. Louis Republic," 23 April 1910, undated
  - "San Francisco Call," 23 April 1910 -- "Finis", undated
  - "Spokane Spokesman Review," 23 April 1910 -- "The Vacant Chair at Stormfield", undated
  - "Washington (D.C.) Evening Star," 23 April 1910, undated
  - "Denver (Col.) Post," 24 April 1910 -- "gone", undated
  - "Chicago Inter-Ocean," 24 April 1910 -- "At a great man's tomb today, undated
  - "Chicago Record-Herald," 24 April 1910, undated
  - "Ohio State Journal," 24 April 1910 -- "Death makes no conquest of this conqueror", undated
  - "Washington (D.C.) Herald," 24 April 1910 -- "Works of cheer still live", undated
  - "New York Evening World, 25 April 1910, undated
  - Zim, 1910? Obit Cartoon? --Elmira's Honored Son, undated
  - Zim: After 1910?, undated
  - "New York American," 1 May 1910, undated
  - Statuette by Amici in Rome Café, undated
  - Merle Johnson's drawing, c. 1910, undated
  - Webster, "The boy whose mother read Tom Sawyer" (before 1915), undated
  - "Life," 9 December 1920, undated
  - "Mentor," May 1924: C. Fornaro -- Twain with umbrella, undated
  - "Saturday Evening Post," Campbell Soup Ad, 1934, undated
  - "Photoplay Magazine," October 1934 -- Budweiser ad, undated
  - "Believe it or Not," 1 November 1935 -- "St. Louis Post-Dispatch", undated
  - Caleb Catlum's America, 1936, undated
  - "Fortune," February 1937: Old Taylor advertisement, includes color photograph, undated
  - In Danish Edition of Stolen White Elephant, undated
  - On Willard Hotel Menu -- Sold in 1943, 1999
  - "Horizon," 23 December, 1945, p. 8, 9 December 1945 p. 18 -- German, undated
  - "New York Herald Tribune," 20 March 1948: Webster, Mark Twain "Chair" -- "The thrill that comes once in a lifetime", undated
  - "Los Angeles Times," 4 November, 1948 -- "As Mark Twain Would Put It", undated
  - James Montgomery Flagg sketch, 12 January 1949, undated
  - "St. Louis Globe-Democrat," 25 January 1949, undated
  - Everett Shinn: Mark Twain in Library, 1951, undated
  - Dutch Quarterly Review, 1981, undated
  - "New York Herald Tribune," 9 May 1952: Old Typesetter, undated
  - David Levine: Three drawings, 1960's, undated
  - H. Lauritzen, Mark Twain's Humor, undated
  - Carl Rose for Bennet Cerf, undated
  - Art Young, undated
  - Old Crow Ad, "TIME," 5 October 1962, undated
  - From "Other Voices (Elmira College)," June 1969, undated
  - Broom-Hilda, 20 July 1971, undated
  - "They'll Do It Everytime," 17 November 1974, undated
  - Gersten, c. 1980 for Quality Paper Backs
  - "Washington Post" Parade Section, 5 April 1981: Mark Twain and His Publisher, undated
  - 1984 Wordcut/Elmira Flier, 2001
  - Paul Pitcher 1980s? 1990s?, undated
  - "New York Times," Gordon Connell, 21 April 1985, undated
  - "Rocky Mountain News," 20 October 1985 -- Win, Lose and Drew
  - Dave Kelley, Essays in Literature, Fall 1985, undated
  - Mark Twain on a Jumping Frog, 1985, 2003
  - V. Courtlandt Johnson, Harper's Magazine, January 1986, undated
  - Ronald Searle: Mark Twain, Steamboat, Tom and Fence, Huck, undated
  - U & LC (Upper and Lower Case) February 1987, undated
  - "Daytona Beach News Journal," 11/8/87, 1987
  - Mark Twain Shirt, c. 1988 -- photograph
  - "San Francisco Chronicle," 10 February 1991 by Val B. Mina, undated
  - "Metropolitan Home," 1991 by Frederick Hart, undated
  - "Chicago Tribune," 18 October 1992
  - 1993 Item -- Will Sleazak
  - Drawings for Mark Twain Festival, Birmingham ALA, March 1993, undated
  - David Tomlinson handout, May 1993
  - "North Carolina Independent," June 30-July 6, 1993
  - Peanuts, 25 July 1995 -- Twain reference, undated
  - Nancy Ohanian, Los Angeles Times, 26 Jan 1997, undated
  - "New York Weekly Standard," 5 May 1997, undated
  - Elmira 1999 for McAvoy Lane Poster
  - Atlantic Monthly, July-August 2001, undated
  - Mike Burrell, 2001
  - Mike Burrell, 2005
  - Mizzou (mag.), Summer 2006
  - Mark Twain in blackface (and color) 2007 or earlier
  - From K. MacDonnell, bought in 2008 -- watercolor
- SERIES 3: MARK TWAIN INTERVIEWS, undated; This series compiled by Louis J. Budd contains photocopies and transcriptions of Mark Twain interviews. Dates reflect the date of the original article and not the date of reproduction. This series contains Budd’s original folder headings and is arranged chronologically
  - Washington National Republican -- "Mark Twain Takes Out a Patent" -- "Probably an authentic summary of Clemens's drolling about his "patent suspenders" and Horace Greeley; No Direct Quotation", September 21, 1871
  - Boston Evening Traveler -- "New Publications" (Hard to Read, January 6, 1874
  - Boston Evening Transcript -- "Soliciting Twain's Subscription", May 29, 1874
  - Boston Evening Journal/Boston Times -- "Mark Twain's Recent Walking Feat"," "Mark Twain as a Pedestrian" -- "Clemens gives details on his abortive walking tour with J.H. Twichell"" (With Notes), November 14, 1874
  - New York SUN and Boston Evening Transcript -- "Mark Twain: An Extract from a Private Letter to a Gentleman of This City," "The Growth of New York: Up Town and Down Town", October 22, 1876
  - Elmira Daily Advertiser -- Mark Twain and Politics -- "Clemens gives his reasons for supporting Rutherford B. Hayes for the presidency" (No Title), December 29, 1876
  - New York SUN -- "Not Quite and Editor", January 26, 1878
  - New York Times, World --MT Sails to Germany, "The Start for Germany"-- "Very long, jocular item as Clemens family embarks; Bayard Taylor gets the most space; though mostly in a joking mood, Clemens indicates that the new travel book will not echo 'Innocents Abroad'", April 12, 1878
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain Interviewed: About New Book on Travel" -- "Rich item dealing mainly with copyright law and with Clemens's conclusions that faults in British were no worse than American ones" (With Notes), May 11, 1879
  - New York Herald -- "Mark Twain's Return/The Great Humorist Delighted to Be Home--How He Passed His Time in Europe" -- "Fairly brief; remarks on forthcoming book and casual remarks about the British aristocracy", September 3, 1879
  - New York SUN -- "Mark Twain Back Again/Freely Expresses His Opinion About Various Things/His View on the English Language, the Danger of the Elevated Railroads, Prunes as a Sea-Going Diet, and Lord Dunraven" -- "Light-weight but amusing; besides topics listed Clemens comments on his forthcoming book", September 3, 1879
  - New York Times -- "Mark Twain Home Again/What He Says About the New Book He Has Written" -- "A jocular account; Clemens makes practical remarks about how much of the new travel book he has written and how he heavily he expects to revise it", September 3, 1879
  - New York World -- "Mr. Twain Again with Us/A Wonderful Book in His Luggage and Much Wonderful Sea-Lore in His Head" -- "After much joking about the sea voyage, nature, and Clemens discusses the progress of his projected travel book", September 3, 1979
  - Hartford Post --"On Sentimental Poetry," "Mark Twain Unfolds a Few Striking Specimens," "A Few Epitaphs" (With Notes, 1880
  - Boston Herald -- "Mark Twain/Samuel L. Clemens' Home in Hartford/The Artistic Surroundings of a Sterling Humorist" -- No direct quotations; seemingly another of the "Mark Twain at Home" pieces; but is based on overnight visit by the reporter (Sylvester Baxter); facts and opinions (as on copyright) come from Clemens--see H.N. Smith and W.M. Gibson, eds., "The Mark Twain-Howells Letter" (Cambridge, Mass., 1960), pp. 311-312, 314-316/, June 20, 1880
  - New York SUN, Knoxville Daily Chronicle -- "The Lookout of the World/Mark Twain's Preparations for a Possible Encounter with a Comet" -- "Most probably spurious; Mark Twain is sitting near Hartford, the roof of his house with a pole, ready to fend of a visible comet if it gets too close to the earth" (With Correspondence), June 27, 1881 - June 28, 1881
  - Montreal (Canada) Gazette -- "An Innocent Abroad" -- "Comments on his lecturing; reminisces about the legislature in the Sandwich Islands, November 28, 1881
  - Boston Evening Traveler -- "New Publications- The Prince and the Pauper", January 6, 1882
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- "An 'Innocent' Interviewed, Mark Twain Pays a Visit to St. Louis" -- "Rails at interviewers; discusses his projected travel book about the Mississippi; develops a fantasy about an expedition to fix location of Hell", May 12, 1882
  - Saint Louis Globe-Democrat -- "Mark Twain Travels, The Famous Humorist Pay a Flying Visit to St Louis/A Round Trip to Mississippi in Search of Book Material" -- "Clemens recalls "Babies" speech; discusses his planned book on the river trip", May 13, 1882
  - Keokuk Daily Constitution, Muscatine Daily Journal -- "Mark Twain Spends a Few Hours in Keokuk, and is Entertained by Some of His Old Friends Here," "Mark Twain: A Short Chat with the Gentleman," "Mark Twain in Muscatine" -- "Gives practical details of his current trip" -- "Brief, no direct quotations; mentions that Clemens recently told anecdote about reciting same certain number of Bible verses for five years" -- "Clemens brief layover; no quotations or summary of significant opinions" (With Correspondence), May 18, 1882 - May 19, 1882
  - Saint Paul and Minneapolis Pioneer Press -- "Mark Twain Not Misrepresented" -- "Brief item; no direct quotations; Clemens on mistrust of interviewers and on reasons for current trip", May 22, 1882
  - Rollingpin's Humorous Illustrated Annual -- "A Day with Mark Twain" (With Correspondence), May, 1882
  - New York Times -- "Mr. Mark Twain Excited/On Seeing the Name of Capt. C. C. Duncan in Print" -- "A blistering but funny tirade, technically an interview; mostly disavowed later by Clemens in New York SUN on August 24, 1883", June 10, 1883
  - Boston Herald -- "Mark Twain and the Police/The Humorist's Experience in a Boston Station House" -- "Not quite an interview but long quotation from Clemens describing his reception at the police station after helping to prevent a suicide", November 16, 1884
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain as a Lecturer/How He Feels When He Gets on the Stage Before an Audience" -- "Clemens discusses how he watches, quakes, and adjusts to the reactions of his audiences", November 20, 1884
  - Baltimore (Md.) American -- "Mark Twain Ideas" -- "Complains mildly about traveling as a lecturer; discusses psychology of audiences and Americanisms of speech", November 29, 1884
  - Rochester (New York) Herald -- "Mark Twain Encountered" -- "Clemens described as loafing the day away; comments on various subjects, such as partnership with G.W. Cable and architecture of his Hartford house", December 8, 1884
  - Toronto Globe -- "An Interview with Mark Twain" -- "Brief, casual; Clemens explains why he went back on his vow never to lecture again" (With Notes), December 9, 1884
  - Detroit Post -- "The Funny Men in Bed/A Post Reporter Disturbs Twain and Interviews Cable" -- "Clemens comments briefly on defects of copyright law, applauds the growing popularity of American humor", December 17, 1884
  - Pittsburgh Chronicle Telegraph -- "A Talk with Mark Twain/His Comments on Authors, Magazines and General Literature" -- "Coherent and cogent; Clemens on a new syndicate for literary materials, his limited taste for fiction (even Hawthorne's), and the social accuracy of Howells' Bartley Hubbard and of "Daisy Miller", December 29, 1884
  - Pittsburgh Penny Press -- "Mark Twain Gets Shaved…and Talks to a Reporter at the Same Time" -- "Clemens jokingly describes himself as the level of a murderer of the English language, asserts seriously that magazine writing is much superior to that of the past", December 29, 1884
  - Pittsburgh Post -- "Mark Twain Gives His Own Experiences with an Interviewer and Jokes at His Own Expense" -- "A lightweight item probably meant to generate free publicity for Twain-Cable tour", December 29, 1884
  - Cincinnati Enquirer -- "Twain and Cable," "The Humorist Interviewed" -- "Clemens does most of the talking; discusses interviews, his days on Territorial Enterprise, Bret Hare", January 3, 1885
  - Louisville (KY) Post -- "A Great Humorist/Mark Twain Gives Some Information Concerning Himself and Partner--How He Met the Reporter and the Instructions He Gave" -- "Clemens casually discusses his reception in the South, his fight for copyright, his treatment by interviewers", January 5, 1885
  - Saint Louis Post-Dispatch -- "Cable and Twain/The Author and the Humorist Arrive in the City To-Day" -- "Clemens in joking mood; does about all the talking, mostly about a rough ride across the Mississippi", January 9, 1885
  - Saint Louis Evening Chronicle -- "Two of a Kind: Samuel Clemens and George W. Cable" -- "Clemens does almost all the talking; he compares Canadian, Northern, Southern, and British audiences and discusses sales of his books", January 9, 1885
  - Chicago Daily News -- "Mark Twain and George Cable Loaded with Enjoyment" -- "Brief but amusing; Clemens jokes about being tired and hungry", January 16, 1885
  - Fort Madison Democrat -- "Mark Twain in Iowa" -- "Long introductory remarks and details, then brief summary of what may have been a long interview; Clemens show interest in Indians", January 21, 1885
  - Minneapolis Tribune -- "An Interesting Chat with Samuel Clemens and George Cable Upon Their Work" -- "Clemens on origin of joint lecture tour and a general sources of Huckleberry Finn; Cable does a good share of talking", January 25, 1885
  - Milwaukee Evening Wisconsin -- "Talk with Mark Twain" -- "Clemens discusses his efforts to get Canadian copyright, the faulty illustration in Huckleberry Finn, and borrowing his pen name from a Mississippi boatman. This may be an interview described in W.J. Anderson, "Tells an Interview He Once Had with Great Humorist," Wisconsin State Journal, April 22, 1910, p. 1", January 29, 1885
  - Lafayette Daily Courier -- "Mark Twain Interviewed/His Views Upon Subjects of Interest" -- "After that familiar version of the origins of reading tour, Clemens joke vigorously about the malodorous local canal, the courthouse, and Cable's soporific effect on audiences", February 6, 1885
  - Detroit Free Press -- "The Re-Mark-Able Twain" -- "Quoted passages are few; much recounting of backstage remarks by Clemens and Cable while the other is performing, February 15, 1885
  - Montreal Daily Star -- "Moments of Samuel Clemens and George Cable", February 20, 1885
  - Minneapolis Tribune -- "Mark Twain in Saint Paul" -- "Brief; Clemens family on way to Kobuk, Iowa; Clemens discusses his habit of working on several books intermittently", June 30, 1886
  - Saint Paul and Minneapolis Pioneer Press -- "Mark Twain Abroad" -- "Clemens comments on modern journalism; brief", June 30, 1886
  - Chicago Tribune -- "Amusing the Children/Thus Does Mark Twain Kill Time While in Chicago" -- "Clemens discusses recent visit to Keokuk, scenery of upper Mississippi River, and neglect of the area by travel writers and social commentators; praises steamboat travel", July 9, 1886
  - Chicago Tribune -- "A Day with Mark Twain/The Genial Humorist at His Summer Home" -- "Edwin J. Park wrote; many small details on the Quarry Farm setting; Clemens has done no writing there during the past summer", September 19, 1886
  - New York World -- "The Insolence of Office" -- "Marginal item; congressional doorkeeper keeps Mark Twain (for a while) from seeing Sunset Cox; Clemens protests that he was once a 'mighty good' reporter in V.A. City", March 23, 1888
  - New York Herald -- "An Interview with the Famous Humorist/He Chats of Past and Present/His Life as a Reporter" -- "In Washington, D.C. Clemens reminisces about 1867-1868", May 19, 1889
  - Boston Journal (Supplement) -- "Mark Twain Speaks His Mind on Interviews/A Pungent Letter from the Great Humorist", July 13, 1889
  - Tacoma (WA) Globe -- "Mark Twain's Latest", December 29, 1889
  - New York Times, Pall Mall Gazette -- "Mark Twain and His Book/The Humorist on the Copyright Question/The Spread of Foreign Notions Not to His Liking--What His English Publisher Dared Not Print" -- "Important comments about Connecticut Yankee", 1889-12-10 & 1889-12-23
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain at Home/An Interesting Visit to the Humorist's Workshop/Talks of His Funny Books/How He Does His Work and Reminiscences of His Most Popular Books--He Labors But Three Months a Year--Replying to Accusations of Plagiarism" -- "Very long item, though reporter is obtrusive; Clemens answers charge that basic idea of Connecticut Yankee was taken from Max Adeler", January 12, 1890
  - Hartford Current -- "Mark Twain's Lawsuit/Dramatization of the 'Prince and the Pauper'" -- "Clemens gives his side of dispute with Edward H. House, January 18, 1890
  - New York Herald -- "Rudyard Kipling on Mark Twain" -- "Bibliog in July-September 1993 MT Circular states that item also ran in Lahore CIVIL AND MILITARY GAZETTE, 23 September 1890; cites article "Kipling and Mark Twain" in Kipling Journal 66, No. 263 (September 1992)" (With Notes), August 17, 1890
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain on Kipling" -- "Fairly long item; deals with Kipling's visit and work, "Diary of Shem," habit of waiting for tank to fill up, and Prince and Pauper lawsuit", August 24, 1890
  - Edward Bob -- "Literary Leaves", May 12, 1991 - May 15, 1991
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain on Humor/T.B. Aldrich the Wittiest Man" -- "Long item with much talk about humor, especially; also on definitions of reverence vs. irreverence", May 31, 1891
  - Berlin National-Zeitung -- "Mark Twain in Berlin" -- "Clemens praises Belen and, unlike hasty visitors to U.S., doubts he will write book about Germany; is relieved to find he is not subject to German taxes and complains about having his royalties taxed in England" (With Correspondence), November 15, 1891
  - New York World -- "Mark Twain's Little Joke/He Registers as 'Mr. Jones, of Gibraltar' To Hide Himself" -- "Brief, with no direct quotation; Clemens claims he wanted to see how long he could remain incognito in New York City", April 5, 1893